[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was wanting to talk about emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, are emotions good or bad?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are they... is there something wrong with them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Should they be cultivated or should they be avoided?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, how can you cultivate?
How can you avoid it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you could give in to your emotions, you know, every little emotion you feel, you could express it and act out of it and, you know, just run with the kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel a sense of love, so you start hugging everyone, telling how much, telling everyone how much you love them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get angry, just get angry, you know, punch, punch someone in the face.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, enjoy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, I asked that question, but I know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, are emotions good or bad?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, some emotions, people will say, are good and other emotions are bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: But are emotions, the world of emotions, is it a good thing or a bad thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have emotions that are good and emotions that are bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But being liable to emotions, that's not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, existentially, that is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, liability to emotions is an issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are liable to these waves that are not in your control, that are sometimes good and sometimes bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, either way, they have to be endured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, either way, you are under the pressure of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not good.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not to say, also, all emotions, in terms of the content, are bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are good emotions, nice emotions, and bad emotions, like unwholesome emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, fundamentally, the nature of emotion is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, well, it puts you in that perilous position.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is being subjected to, you know, feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fundamentally what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, people tend to not think about the feelings or emotions when those are good or when those are not too threatening or not too... not reminding, you know, not dangerous and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those things change.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can get some feelings that will be revealing the
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger, the unpleasantness, and that you don't know the escape from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, and then you realize, ah, feeling is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be in a position of, kind of, pinned down by an unpleasant feeling of something that happened, that you don't know how to escape from, if you haven't been cultivating gratuitous ownership
[SPEAKER_00]: Appropriation and carelessness in regard to the feeling per se.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that unwholesome type of cultivation happens basically through just, you know, accepting the pleasant feeling, taking it for granted, and assuming that you can always outrun the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't realize that either way, you're deeply bound with a feeling which is not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like that simile I gave before, I think, I don't know if you recorded it, or maybe in just some of the talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, you basically, you find yourself, like, riding a horse that you can't get off.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't come down from it, and it doesn't listen to you, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it goes where it wants to go, and when those things that it wants to see are nice and agreeable, you enjoy the ride,
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, sometimes, something else takes its fancy, and it goes wild, and runs to the sort of, you know, thorny bushes, and cliffs, and rough stones, and you fall off, and then you're dragged, and then you realize, okay, so riding a horse is a dangerous experience, because I'm not in the control of a horse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can pretend everything is fine, when the horse is sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, you know, taking a slow stride along the beach or something, when it's very pleasant and easy, but then when it's galloping through some wild woodland, and I'm getting cut up and beaten, oh, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't want to wait for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to start training the horse before it gets into the, you know, areas and positions that will harm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's the same with your mind and same with the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're only... if you're enjoying the presence of your mind and your thoughts and the life when feelings are good, you are making yourself liable to then equally suffer when those feelings change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to experience bad feelings, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just not having enough of the good feelings that you had is already felt badly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of your dependence on good emotions and good feelings and good moods, you become even more sensitive, more liable to the bad ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what is bad is relative, from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not having enough of a pleasant emotion is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were not so dependent on the unpleasant emotions... sorry, if you were not so dependent on the pleasant emotions,
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't be so quick, basically, to fall into that resistance of the unpleasant ones, because the mind wouldn't move, because the mind is not that dependent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of dependence on emotions and feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that you can't... not that you can stop them, but you can certainly not appropriate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha would say, not welcome them, not delight in them, not... not lose perspective in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to be creating a broader context in regard to whatever you're feeling here and now that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not trying to get rid of it, and you're certainly not trying to indulge it, and you're certainly not trying to explain it and psychologize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you're trying to do is remain unmoved by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you do so by developing the full understanding of that context, that, you know, that fundamentally they're unownable, they come on their own, like the waves, and that you are the one who chooses to jump into them and then get all wet and soaked and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... so then... so someone might say, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I love love.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love excitement and that passionate drive, adventure and all that, those exciting emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they strive just to have that, you know, and focus just on that part.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is there a way just to have those pleasant feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is focusing on just that possibility of pleasant emotions a good thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is it possible just to have pleasant emotions?
[SPEAKER_01]: First of all, is it possible just to have that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole thing is, if somebody wants to focus on that, yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will experience that degree of happiness, that degree of sensual joy, to that extent, for that amount of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then... And if that's their choice, yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing, like, morally wrong with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless, of course, their actions are harming others, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, universally speaking, from the point of view of a human experience that is liable to certain things, that same person, if they were to have some wisdom, or if they're interested in developing wisdom, should ask themselves, okay, well, what are the prerequisites for me being able to focus only on pleasant experiences, chase them, get as much as I want, enjoy the life, enjoy sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the necessary conditions for that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, being alive is the first condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being healthy is the second condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having functioning senses is the third condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pretty much, you know, having strength and zeal is the condition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, am I in control of those conditions that are necessary for me to be able to chase the happiness and enjoy it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that thought will be enough to, you know, reveal the anxiety underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, sure, you can chase the pleasures, if you want, by ignoring the nature of your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you are not in control of that horse, that is liable to sickness, aging, and death, and it will take you, basically, when it goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your happiness, that you're getting on account of that basis, is very limited, very perilous, and very intoxicating, in a sense of, uh, it makes you forget the true nature of a situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you could die at any given moment, that you could get sick at any given moment, that your senses will fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, can you enjoy the beautiful sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, if you can't see, hear, smell, taste, or touch?
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is like what... that is... that is the kind of the most frightening idea a person would have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine you... you get into that... how is it called medically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a locked-in syndrome, you know, where basically you are alive inside, but your senses, everything is just shut out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have no perception of the external world, yet you are aware of yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is basically a situation at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what existence is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that these, eh... external sense objects, you know, being inducive of lust, and you taking them for granted, and seeking them further outside, makes you basically forget that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes you forget your current situation, that you're always fully enclosed within yourself, and there is no way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly not in that... external sense that you would be, eh... seeking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that universal point of view,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's not good, then, to be blind like that and just intoxicated and infatuated with the current pleasures and happiness and emotions you're feeling, because it masks the real nature of your situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, from your individual point of view, if that's what you want to do, yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll get the results and you'll pay the price, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, as you say, you know, you are not in control of your senses, your body, you know, you get diseases and so on, or your wealth and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, the external things that you are dependent upon, say, for example, your children,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, so you... you love seeing, hearing, experiencing your children, you know, watching them grow up, and it's... and it's such a wonderful experience, the birth, and the way they start learning about things, and it's... they're so cute, and it's fascinating, and you're just overflowing with joy and love, and then they get cancer, or someone hits them, you know, have an accident on the road, hits them with a car, and now
[SPEAKER_01]: You're so dependent on that thing, out there, so far away from your your body, which you are not even in control of, let alone another person's body, and you've spilled out so far, so emotionally dependent, when that thing changes in a horrible way, or, you know, just in a simple way, that's disagreeable to you in some, even a small way, you're completely shattered.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, your life is
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, because you've been riding really, really high up, you've been high up, and now that thing came crashing and you didn't have time to come down safely.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that dependence on family and children and possessions and wealth and things that are even more removed out of your control.
So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you know, if you're speaking to a person who is dependent on those external things, very emotionally dependent, and, you know, it is a wonderful thing to love your children, to be kind to them, you know, but there is that danger there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the reality of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, people will often then kind of jump into conclusion that, ah, so it's dangerous, so you're saying it's bad to love children.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, as I said, it's not a moral question.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's from the universal point of view of your situation, what is basically, eh... skillful, what is unskillful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's unskillful to live on top of a tree that somebody is cutting and you refuse to come down.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is unskillful, but you're still free to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will be responsible for everything that happens to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, the choice is on the person.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if, you know, if they don't absolutely know any other way to live, any form of withdrawal of sense restraint, well, the most you can do is encourage them at least to be virtuous within that perilous situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if a person does want to practice, and is familiar with the dhamma, and is in that position of depending on external circumstances to a great extent, well then, yeah, you might just want to remind them of the implicit peril and the sense of urgency that's right there, visible to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's that having a perspective on that thing that you love, you know, having a perspective that, yes, things could, you know, you could experience good things, you know, pleasant feelings, so to speak, but you can equally experience painful feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things can be going quite well for you, and then all of a sudden, you know, you get a disease, there's an accident, there's a murder.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things happen in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can focus on all the positive things in the world, all the lovely things, the adventures you can have, the excitement, the new discoveries, and so on, but
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just see that part of the world, you are narrow-minded in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the other part affects you, you are going to be, you know, surprised in a horrific kind of way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to be... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, a person can also then choose to just be focused on the negative and equally lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to find the middle ground and then you will feel responsibility on account of it and the weight of your actions and you will choose much more wisely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even, as I said, even without needing to renounce the whole world and become a monk and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you basically, through your own reflection, see that, yes, you kind of don't like to think about, you know, what-ifs of the negative kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only like to focus on the positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's why you should think about the negatives.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what ifs?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, oh, I must, like, you know, get rid of my children and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but I must broaden the context and prevent that narrowing of my mind to occur on account of being absorbed and taking this pleasure for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And equally, if all you're doing is just seeing the negative and thinking about the murders and accidents and so on, you could equally lose perspective then and recognize, yeah, but that's not happening all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that life is all about that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, you could then, kind of, you know, broaden that narrowness by actually thinking on the good side.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the, you know, there is friendship in the world, there is kindness, there is wholesome, there is virtue, there are results of good actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, basically, keep the balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn how to stay in the middle, regardless of what your tendency is, whether to just focus on the positive and ignore the negative, or just to dwell and wallow in negative, and just dismiss and be cynical in regard to any positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are actually sustaining that balance, then, yes, as I said, your actions will feel differently, the weight behind them will feel differently, and your joy on account of children, or misery on account of world, will be something you will feel responsibly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you will know you're responsible for that state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you won't be projecting the fault onto the world, nor would you be projecting that all the happiness just comes from the world, and all I need to do is protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you would see that it comes from your state of mind, where it chooses, basically, and how it chooses to attend things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and I was, I was, I was thinking about, you know, that, so, you have people who just go with their emotions, no restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: No perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you have also this kind of emotion of indifference, you know, crushing your feelings, so to speak, keeping them locked away.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel them, but you you keep them subdued, you know, like a like a soldier or a warrior.
[SPEAKER_01]: The stoic indifference, stoic indifference, you know, managing your emotions, not letting them get out of hand, so overpowering them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are, you are experiencing pleasure, you're experiencing a heightened, you know, state of emotion, but you control yourself, you restrain yourself, and you just get the job done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you want, you need to do in your life, you just get it done.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: You overpower your emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kind of ignore them in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, which is strange.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... you can't really ignore them.
[SPEAKER_01]: To ignore them, you need to know that they are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so you're kind of suppressing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I want to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're kind of suppressing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you get this person who's like the stoic, indifferent soldier, warrior, you know, shoot some, kill people, and don't... try not to feel what that feels like.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the original stoicism was about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, I think people might think that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to depress your feelings and sort of... Well, that's the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just trying to deny the reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The existence of the fact that you are still feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not being genuinely unmoved by feeling because you understood the unknown ability on account of your virtues and skillful behavior developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're just trying to cover up the fact that you are still liable, but you're just trying to take even further control and basically kind of cement it all with your attitude, no, I don't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that cannot be sustained either.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that attitude is also dependent on the same things that your feelings and your joys depend on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends on the circumstances, it depends on your determination, it depends on your intention, your health.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends on the current set of circumstances that are not too challenging, so that you can sustain the determination to not feel anything and overpower everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when things change, eh... again, when the health goes, senses start to fail, you start being overwhelmed from all sides, even that intention will go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has a limited... it has a basically, eh... it has its own shelf life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, there is the gratification in emotions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are pleasant emotions, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the danger of emotions, you know, being... you're just moved by them, you're making decisions upon them, whatever you feel, that's how you act, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's that danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how not to be moved by emotions?
[SPEAKER_01]: How
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will be able to not be moved by emotions, which are on the level of your mind, if you have sufficiently practiced not being moved by all the things that are kind of the results of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stopped acting carelessly, without perspective, unwholesomely with your body,
[SPEAKER_00]: And sustain that as your day-to-day living, that perspective of certain non-action, you know, the aggregate of virtue we spoke about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equally, if you... if you have ceased all the unwholesome actions, actions by speech, they were rooted in... in all these other, like, subtle movements due to emotions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, you'll be able to equally remain unmoved and not act out of the mental state of... of whatever you're currently feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you cannot live your life
[SPEAKER_00]: The way it is, which is undermined, life undermined and controlled, but influenced by emotions, and somehow magically expect to just be able to pull the emotion part out, without everything else changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, that's like putting, pulling the bottom, the, you know, like a house of cards, pulling the bottom card out, and expecting the the whole kind of creation to remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything is rooted in how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's not like I must stop doing everything, because that's another doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's impossible to accomplish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop not doing of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can direct your doing in the direction that will tame your mind, reduce the dependence of you on your emotions and pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about killing the horse and strangling it while you're riding it, because you'll come crashing with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about training it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about not going where you know you shouldn't be going,
[SPEAKER_00]: And developing that strength and ability of sense restraint and then sustaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... it's... there is no other, like... People might assume, oh, there's some... some great magical revelation will come out of my sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense restraint will come out of the sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And once you start seeing that, you see a direct link then to how you develop and train that horse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_00]: Like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: By preventing it from doing things it shouldn't be doing, by making it do things that it doesn't want to do, but we both know are good for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, again, skillful reflection, skillful behavior, precepts, and sustaining mindfulness on account of those actions throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what you should do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will know that that in itself is already a benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is already a reward.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the mind settles, when the horse settles into that, then you get even a higher reward.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you are the one riding and controlling the horse and telling it where to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot drag you into the thorny bushes where you're gonna get strangled and, you know, with your head knocked off and so on, because you are in charge where it goes and it listens to you now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is true, pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that takes to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is there is a state of mind that can be developed, that is, that can last, you can say, last forever, for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, that lasts as long as you're alive, not forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that is what you, in a way, that's what you're talking about, that state of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: A state of wholesome peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, you know, as I said, depending on how much
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it depends how much you allow that horse to still engage with its wild desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that extent, you can expect kind of the corresponding peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't allow it as much, you can have a greater peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you still let it run wild every now and then, well, to that extent, you are diminishing your possibility of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, still, any effort you make towards taming, it will result to that degree of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's never gonna go to waste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is ultimately what everybody wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the reason people become infatuated with the, you know, pleasant experiences of the horse riding in the simile, is because of the peaceful pleasures that they get from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The satisfying, the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, gratification results in peace, results in temporary calmness of subsiding of your desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you arrived at them through violent scratching of the itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's going to come back even worse because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, fundamentally, even pursuit of the desires and the pleasures and sensuality is done with the peace as the ultimate result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you don't want to be sense-restrained, if you don't want peace of this kind, you actually still want peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look deep down,
[SPEAKER_00]: The end project of all the, you know, desires and gains and possessions and joys and emotions that people have, is that peaceful pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why also people would then immediately jump into conclusion, into assumption that, oh, wow, this is so nice, and immediately assume that it will last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just too nice to think that it won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that whole notion of eternal and permanent is not some, like a, you know, a philosophical glitch in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's the result of your emotional dependence on pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You naturally assume that this will never change, because just thinking that it might change undermines that peace of that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you admit it to yourself or not, you want peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just what you do in order to get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how you choose to go about it, that's what's going to determine whether you're going to get it or not, and whether you're going to pay a price for it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I... that kind of peace, actual peace, you know, being unmoved by a pleasant feeling, being unmoved by unpleasant feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: That that kind of... the peace to that extent, that you're still actually having pleasant feelings and unpleasant feelings, but you're unmoved by them, that peace is kind of horrifying for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I explain to them, that kind of peace is absolutely horrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... That's because even the peace that they know, they have no understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were to actually develop at least some basic wisdom in regard to their own situation, without, you know, giving things up and so on and enduring, they would... they would... well, it would be easy for them to come... come to terms with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... they're so unaware that any notion of... of that kind of stilling and, eh... and what you will be describing as peaceful, it just feels like, oh, that means I'm dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's people in the suttas who were scared when the Buddha would describe nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else is there, other than, you know, if you're not feeling something, you're dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you'd... or you, you know, you're alive, but you're kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It means they're so unaware, even of the nature of their feelings, that they don't even see that they often don't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yet they're not dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it would have meant.
[SPEAKER_00]: The neutral feeling is completely unseen, not understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see it and understand it, it will actually feel pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason they can even...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason they can even be scared or horrified by the idea of peace is because deep down they recognize what that neutral feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means they know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just refuse to admit it to themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of their dependence on that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure, the dependence on that kind of movement, activity, happening, engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the only way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what I said, you know, like, it's kind of relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't start as soon as you're born by that high dependence on a pleasant activity and engagement and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop it carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why people who are super hyperactive, always engaged, even when they're slightly less engaged, still very much engaged, but slightly less engaged, mind will be filled with boredom and dread, and because not enough is happening, because their minds became even more dependent on even high level of activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no end to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is like an addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you take, the more you'll need to take.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, not getting emotional is a sign that, you know, you are handling your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, hmm, it depends, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I know what you mean, but if somebody hears it like that, it means, okay, so I must just prevent emotions from happening and that's how I'm handling my feelings, no?
[SPEAKER_00]: You must not be acting out of your emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you're handling your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're able to let them arise to the extent they want to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you won't be moved by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you're handling your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, managing your feelings, managing your emotions, is still management.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still having to deal... Well, you're still acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're overwhelmed by an emotion, thus you are needing to handle it.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you're feeling, whatever emotions are pressuring you,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the threshold of the virtue of the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your container.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that, you focus on not losing perspective in a situation for as long as the emotion lasts, and not giving in to the pressure to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not going to be perfect in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be still doing it, to some extent, out of desire to manage it, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if these, sort of, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: frameworks are protected, that motivation will subside and you'll start doing it more and more rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like that, as you're saying before, so you handle your emotions, don't act out of them, you know, you can then gain a restraint and so on, you gain a perspective on your feelings,
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can start understanding their nature, what the fundamental nature of feelings are, and thus be free from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So when, no matter how intense they come, manifest... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that point, you would be able to start seeing that freedom from feeling is not freedom from
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings arising, it's freedom from basically, eh... you owning them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot own them now, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're truly seen as impersonal, as impersonal things out there in the world that come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they cannot move you, because it's not yours, not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's truly not felt.